<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An act for discovering, convicting, and repressing of popish recusants. At the Parliament begun at Westminster the 17th day of September, anno Domini 1656.</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21827</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99890710</idno>
  <idno type="VID">190687</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240923082</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1030</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E.1065[31]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 21.b.16[16]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4821</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99890710</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99890710e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21827)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 190687)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C23:2[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An act for discovering, convicting, and repressing of popish recusants. At the Parliament begun at Westminster the 17th day of September, anno Domini 1656.</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills and John Field, printers to His Highness the Lord Protector.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Enacted: 26 June 1657.</note>
                  <note>On A1r: last word in first line of text: 'a'; first word under initial: 'whereof'; last word in last full line of text: 'such'.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Catholics --  England --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:190687:1"/>
            <p>AN ACT FOR Discovering, Convicting, and Repressing OF Popish Recusants.</p>
            <p>At the Parliament begun at <hi>Westminster</hi> the 17<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Day of <hi>September, Anno Domini</hi> 1656.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>coat of arms of the Commonwealth</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills</hi> and <hi>John Field,</hi> Printers to His Highness the Lord Protector. 1657.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:190687:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:190687:2"/>
            <head>AN ACT FOR Discovering, Convicting and Repressing OF Popish Recusants.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuch as there is of late a great increase of Popish Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sants within this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, occasioned by the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of putting the Laws in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution against them, by reason whereof great danger may follow thereupon to the Publique Peace; They being persons very active in mischievous Plots and Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies, as appears by their late Barbarous and bloody Rebellion and Cruelties in <hi>Ireland</hi> and this Nation: For prevention therefore of the rise and growth of so great a Mischief, His Highness the Lord Protector, and the Parliament of the Common-wealth of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> do declare and Enact; And be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That all Iustices of Assize and Goal-delivery, and all Iustices of Peace in their open Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Sessions of Peace, within the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> shall give in charge in to the Grand Iuries, diligently to enquire, and present the names of all such
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:190687:3"/> persons, being of the age of sixteen years, as are suspected or reputed to be Papists, or Popishly affected, and that upon every such presentment, the Iustices of Assize, and Goal-delivery, and Iustices of the Peace, shall in open Sessions make Proclamation, by which it shall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that every person so presented as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, shall personally appear at the next Assizes and General Goal-delivery, or at the next gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Quarter Sessions respectively, to be holden for the Shire, Division, Limit or Liberty, and there to take and Subscribe the Oath of Abju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, The form of which Oath hereafter followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I <hi>A. B.</hi> do abjure and renounce the Popes Supremacy and Authority over the Catholique Church in General, and over my self in particular: And I do believe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not the true Church; And that there is not any Transubstantiation in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, or in the Elements of Bread and Wine, after Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secration thereof, by any person whatsoever. And I do also believe, that there is not any Purgatory; And that the Consecrated Hoast, Crucifixes or Images ought not to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped, neither that any Worship is due unto any of them; And I also believe that Salvation cannot be merited by works; And I do sincerely Testify and Declare, That the Pope neither of himself nor by any Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:190687:3"/>
               <hi>of the Church or See of <hi>Rome,</hi> or by any other means with any other, hath any power or authority to depose the Chief Magistrate of these Nations, or to dispose of any the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries or Territories thereunto belonging, or to Authorize any Foreign Prince or State to invade or annoy him or them, or to discharge any of the people of these Nations from their Obedience to the Chief Magistrate; or to give License or leave to any of the said people to bear Arms, raise Tumults, or to offer any violence or hurt to the person of the said Chief Magistrate, or to the State or Government of these Nations, or to any of the People thereof. And I do further swear, That I do from my heart abhor, detest and abjure this Damnable Doctrine and Position, That Princes, Rulers or Governours, which be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated or Deprived by the Pope, may, by vertue of such Excommunication or Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, be killed, murthered, or deposed from their Rule or Government, or any outrage or violence don unto them by the people that are under them, or by any other whatsoever upon such pretence. And I do further swear, That I do believe that the Pope, or Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath no Authority, Power or Jurisdiction whatsoever, within <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> or any or either of them, or the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:190687:4"/>
               <hi>or Territories belonging to them, or any or either of them; And all Doctrines in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the said points, I do abjure and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, without any equivocation, mental re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation, or secret evasion whatsoever, taking the words by me spoken according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and usual meaning of them, And I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve no power derived from the Pope or Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other person, can ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve me from this my Oath, and I do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all pardons and dispensations to the contrary: <hi>So help me God.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That if at such next Assizes, and general Goal delivery, or at such next Quarter Sessions, to be holden as aforesaid, the same person so proclaimed, shall not make appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance upon Record, and in open Sessions take and subscribe the said Oath, (which Oath the said Iustices respectively are hereby Impow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to administer) Then upon such default, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Recorded, such person so making default, shall be adjudged a Popish Recusant convict, to all intents and purposes whatsoever.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That four times in every year, <hi>viz.</hi> once in every Quarter, and eight and twenty dayes at the least before the beginning of the Quarter Sessions of Peace, to be holden for any County, Division, Limit, or Liberty, the respective Iustices of the Peace for such Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Division, Limit, or Liberty; or two or more
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:190687:4"/> of them, shall issue their Warrants to all the Constables, and Church-wardens of every Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, Chappel, Town, and Hamlet, within such their respective County, Division, Limit, and Liberty, requiring them, at a certain day and place to be mentioned in such Warrants, which day shall be at least fourteen dayes before such Quarter Sessions, to present, upon their Oathes, unto the said Iustices, the Names, Sirnames, Additions, and Places of abode, of all such persons, being of the Age of sixteen years, as are suspected or reputed to be Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists, or Popishly affected: And that upon every such Presentment upon Oath, (which Oath the said Iustices are hereby Impowred to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minister) such Iustices shall forthwith issue their Warrants to the Constables, thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring them to summon every such person so Presented, either by delivering unto every of them a Note in writing, or leaving the same at their dwelling House, or usual place of abode of such person so Presented, to appear person<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at the next Quarter Sessions to be holden for such County, Division, Limit, or Liberty respectively: And that at such next Quarter Sessions, the said Iustices of the Peace, unto whom any such Presentment shall be made, shall deliver every such Presentment in open Sessions, to be Recorded; And all such Consta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, unto whom any such Warrant of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons shall be directed, shall likewise then and there, return such their respective Warrants, to be entred upon Record, and make Oath of the due execution thereof, which Oath the said Iustices of Peace in their Quarter Sessions, are hereby Impowred to administer: And if at
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:190687:5"/> such Quarter Sessions, such persons so Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned as aforesaid, shall not make appearance upon Record, and in open Sessions, take and subscribe the said Oath, then the Iustices shall in open Sessions make Proclamation, by which it shall be Commanded, That every Person so Presented and Summoned as aforesaid, shall personally appear at the next Quarter Sessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be holden for the said County, Division, Limit, or Liberty respectively, then and there to take the said Oath: And if at such next Quarter Sessions to be holden as aforesaid, any such person so Proclaimed, shall not make appearance upon Record, and in open Sessions take and subscribe the said Oath, then upon such default Recorded, such person so making default, shall be adjudged a Popish Recusant Convict, to all intents and purposes whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That if the Iustices of Peace with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in any County, Division, Limit, or Liberty, or any two or more of them, shall suspect any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, being of the age of sixteen years, to be a Papist, or Popishly affected, it shall be lawful for such Iustices, by their Warrants, to send for, and to cause every such person so suspected, to become bound by Recognizance, in the sum of One hundred pounds, to appear at the next Quarter Sessions of the Peace, to be holden for the said County, Division, Limit, or Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty respectively, then and there to subscribe the said Oath: And if such person so suspected, shall refuse to become so bound, then it shall be lawfull unto such Iustices, to commit such person so suspected, unto safe Custody, there
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:190687:5"/> to remain without Bail or Mainprise, untill such next Quarter Sessions, to be holden as aforesaid: And if at such next Quarter Sessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the same Person so bound or imprisoned, shall not make appearance upon Record, and in open Sessions take and subscribe the said Oath, then upon such default Recorded, such Person so making default, shall be adjudged a Popish Recusant convict to all intents and purposes whatsoever: And if such person so suspected, shall not upon any such Warrant be apprehended and brought before such Iustices, to become bound by Recognizance as aforesaid, then such Iustices shall and may, at the next Quarter Sessions, to be holden as aforesaid, Present the names of every such person so by them suspected, and upon such Presentment Recorded, the Iustices shall in open Sessions make Proclamation, by which it shall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that every such person so presented, shall, at the next Quarter Sessions, to be holden as aforesaid, make appearance upon Record, and then and there in open Sessions, take and subscribe the said Oath: And if at the then next Quarter Sessions, to be holden as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, the same person so Proclaimed, shall not make his appearance upon Record, and in open Court take and subscribe the said Oath, Then upon such default Recorded, such person so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king default, shall be adjudged a Popish Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusant convict to all intents and purposes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That it shall be lawfull to His High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness the Lord Protector, and His Successors, by Process out of the Court of Exchequer, To
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:190687:6"/> Seize, and take into His, and their hands, to the use of the Common-wealth, Two parts, in three parts to be divided, of all the Debts, Goods and Chattels of every person any ways so Convict of Popish Recusancy as aforesaid; And also to Seize and take into His and their hands two parts, in three parts to be divided, of all Lands, Tenements, Hereditaments, Leases, Farms, and Copy-hold Lands, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of any such Popish Recusant convict, or any in trust for him or her, shall be Seized, or Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed at the time of such Conviction, or at any time after, and the same to Possess, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy to the use of the Common-wealth, untill such person so Convict shall conform by taking the said Oath; Saving to His Highness the Lord Protector, and his Successors, and every person and persons, Bodies politique and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, their Heirs and Successours, (other then such persons so Convict, and his, and her Heirs, and all claiming to his, her, or their use, or in trust for him, her, or them) all and all manner of Leases, Rents, Conditions, and other Rights and Titles whatsoever, had, made, or done <hi>bona fide,</hi> and without Fraud, or Covin before such Conviction.</p>
            <p>Provided alwaies, That His said Highness the Lord Protector, or His Successors, shall not Seize, or take in to His or their two third parts, (but leave unto such person so Convict) his or her Mansion House, as part of his, or her third part.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That every such Conviction of any person for Popish Recusancy, shall, from the Iustices before whom the Record of such Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:190687:6"/> shall remain, be Estreated and certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, into His Highness Court of Exchequer, before the end of the Term next En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uing such Conviction, in such convenient certainty, for time and other Circumstances, that the said Court of Exchequer may thereupon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Process for seizure of two third parts of all Lands, Tenements, Leases, Farms, Copie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Lands, Goods and Chattels of every person so convict as aforesaid. And that every such Certificate and Estreat, shall be entred upon the Docquet in the Treasurers Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers Office, and from thence to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Clerk of the Extracts, and by him immediately to the Clerk of the Pipe, there to be Enrolled, &amp; from thence returned to the said Clerk of the Extracts, to remain in safe custody for a Comptrol for His Highness service, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the course of the Court of Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer: And that Schedules thereof be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with made from the said great Roll, for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess, to be thereupon issued by Commission, or otherwise, by the said Remembrancer, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of and seize two third parts of all the Lands, Tenements, Goods and Chattels, of every such person so convict as aforesaid; And that upon return thereof, every inquisition and seizure shall be Enrolled in the Office of the said Remembrancer, and from thence charged in the said great Roll, and from thence forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with scheduled and delivered unto the Auditors of the respective Counties, to the end his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness may be duly answered upon accompt by His Receivers of such Counties, of all such two third parts of all such Lands, Tenements, Goods and Chattels; And that every dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:190687:7"/> hereafter to be made by the said Court of Exchequer, of any Lands, Tenements, Goods or Chattels, so charged in the said great Roll, and from thence Scheduled and Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered unto the said Auditors as aforesaid, shall be entred upon Record in the said great Roll, and be from thence Certified unto every such respective Auditor as formerly.</p>
            <p>Provided alwaies, and be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That if any person Convict of Popish Recusancy as aforesaid, shall at any time come before the Iustices of Assize and Goal-delivery, or before the Iustices of the Peace in their quarter Sessions for such County, Division, Limit, or Liberty respective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, where such person was Convict, and in open Sessions take and subscribe the said Oath, such Iustices shall forthwith Record such sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, and certifie the same into His Highness Court of Exchequer, and then upon such Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate Recorded, such person, so submitting and Certified, shall be Freed and Discharged of and from all Seizures, Penalties, and Losses, which the same person might otherwise sustain and bear, for, or by reason of such persons Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction for Popish Recusancy; And if any such person so Convict as aforesaid, or any other person, whose Estate is now under Seizure, or Sequestration, for Popish Recusancy, shall at any time come before the Barons of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, and in open Court take and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe the said Oath, (which Oath the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons are hereby impowred to administer) Then upon such Submission Recorded, the Person so Submitting shall forthwith be Freed and Discharged, of and from all Seizures, Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:190687:7"/> Penalties and Losses, which the same person might otherwise sustain and bear, for, or by reason of such persons Conviction or Sequestration for Popish Recusancy.</p>
            <p>Provided also, and be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that if any person being so convict or sequestred for Popish Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sancy, as aforesaid, shall happen to dye, his or her Heir, being of the full age of sixteen years, then such Heir shall, from the decease of such person, quietly and peaceably have, hold, pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess and enjoy the Estate of such person, and the Rents and Profits thereof, Freed and Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of and from all Seizures, Sequestra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Penalties and Losses, which the same Heir might otherwise sustain and bear, for, or by reason of such his or her Ancestors Popish Recusancy; So that such Heir do or shall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the end of the Term, next after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cease of such Ancestors, come before the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons of the Exchequer, and in open Court take and subscribe the said Oath; But if such Heir do not or shall not then come before the said Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, and take and subscribe the said Oath, as aforesaid; Then such Heir shall have, hold, possess and enjoy such Estate, and the Rents and Profits thereof freed and discharged as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, from such time only, as such Heir shall come before the said Barons, and take and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe the said Oath as aforesaid, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>And if the Heir of any such person so Convict or Sequestred for Popish Recusancy, shall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be within the Age of sixteen years, at the time of the death of such his or her Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors, Then the Guardian or Guardians of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:190687:8"/> such Heir, shall, from the decease of such An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestor, be permitted quietly and peaceably to receive the Rents and Profits of such Estate; so that such Guardian and Guardians, being approved or appointed by the said Barons, do give Security in the said Court of Exchequer, to account once every year, before one of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors of the said Court, for such Rents and Profits, over and above such yearly allowance, for the Education and Maintenance of such Heir, as the said Barons shall appoint, and to pay the Residue of such Rents and Profits, over and above such Allowances, unto such Heir; So that such Heir do, and shall before the end of the Term next after such Heir shall attain the full Age of sixteen years, come before the said Barons of the Exchequer, and in open Court take and subscribe the said Oath; And if such Heir do not, or shall not then come before the said Barons, and subscribe the said Oath as aforesaid, Then forthwith to pay the Resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of such Rents and Profits into the Receipt of the Exchequer, to the use of His Highness and the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that if such Heir do or shall, before the end of such next Term, come before the said Barons, and in open Court take and subscribe the said Oath, then such Guardian and Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians shall pay unto such Heir, such Residue of the said Rents and Profits, And such Heir shall have, hold, possess and enjoy the same, and also the Estate of such his or her Ancestour, freed and discharged of and from all Seizures, Sequestrations, Penalties and Losses, which otherwise such Heir might sustain and bear, for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:190687:8"/> or by reason of such Ancestors Popish Recusan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. But if such Heir do not or shall not, before the end of such next Term, come before the said Barons, and take and subscribe the said Oath, then such Guardian and Guardians shall forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with pay the Residue of such Rents and Profits into the Receipt of the Exchequer, to the use of His Highness and the Commonwealth; And then such Heir shall have, hold, possess and enjoy the Estate of such Ancestor, and the Rents and Profits thereof, freed and discharged as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, from such time only, as such Heir shall come before the said Barons, and take and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe the said Oath, and not before.</p>
            <p>Provided also, and be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That if any person whose Estate now is, or hereafter shall be seized or sequestred for Popish Recusancy, hath given, conveyed, or otherwise setled, or shall hereafter give, convey, or any waies settle, by Deed, Will or otherwise, all or any part of such Estate so Seized or Sequestred as aforesaid, or any Rent, Sum of money or other profit, out of the same or any part thereof, to or for the use, benefit, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoof of the Wife, Childe or Children of any such person as shall happen to die, such Wife, Childe and Children respectively being of the full age of sixteen years, Then such Wife, Childe and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren respectively shall, from the decease of such person, have, hold, possess and enjoy the full benefit of such Gift, Conveyance, or other setle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, freed and discharged, of and from all such Seizures, Sequestrations, Penalties and Losses, for or by reason of the Popish Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sancy of such person so dying, so that such Wife, Childe and Children respectively, do and shall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:190687:9"/> the end of the Term next after the decease of such person come before the said Barons of the Exchequer, and in open Court take and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe the said Oath; But if such Wife, Childe and Children respectively, do not or shall not then come before the said Barons, and take and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said Oath as aforesaid, Then such Wife, Childe and Children shall have, hold, possess, and enjoy, the full benefit of such Gift, Convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance or other Settlement, freed and discharged as aforesaid, from such time only as such Wife, Childe and Children respectively, shall come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the said Barons and take and subscribe the said Oath as aforesaid, and not before; And if such Wife, Childe or Children shall happen to be within the age of sixteen years, at the time of the death of any such person, then the Guardian or Guardians, of such Wife, Childe or Children, respectively, shall, from the decease of such Person, be permitted to take the full benefit of such Gift, Conveyance, or other setlement, so that such Guardian and Guardians respective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, being approved or appointed by the said Barons, to give Security in the said Court of Exchequer, to accompt once every year, before one of the Auditors of the said Court, for all such Rents, Profits, or sums of Money, as such Guardian and Guardians respectively, shall or might any waies receive over and above such yearly allowances, as the Barons of the Exchequer shall appoint for the education and maintenance of any such Wife, Childe and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren respectively, and to pay the Residue of such Rents, Profits, and Sums of money, over and above such Allowances unto such Wife, Childe and Children respectively; so that such Wife,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:190687:9"/> Childe and Children respectively, do and shall, before the end of the Term next after such Wife, Childe and Children shall attain their respective Ages of sixteen years, come before the said Barons of the Exchequer, and in open Court take and subscribe the said Oath; But if such Wife, Childe and Children respectively, shall not then come before the said Barons, and take and subscribe the said Oath as aforesaid, then such Guardian and Guardians respectively, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to pay the Residue of such Rents, Profits and Sums of money, into the Receipt of the Exchequer, to the use of his Highness the Lord Protector, and the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That if such Wife, Childe and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren respectively, do and shall, before the end of such next Term, come before the said Barons, and take and subscribe the said Oath as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, then such Guardian and Guardians shall pay unto such Wife, Childe and Children re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectively, such Residue of the said Rents, Profits and Sums of money, and such Wife, Childe and Children shall have, hold, possess and enjoy the same, and also the full benefit of such Gift, Conveyance, and other Setlement, Freed and Discharged of &amp; from all Seizures, Sequestrations, Penalties and Losses, for or by reason of the Popish Recusancy of such person so dying as aforesaid; But if such Wife, Childe or Children respectively, shall not then come before the Barons, and take and subscribe the said Oath as aforesaid, then such Guardian and Guardians shall pay such Resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of such Rents, Profits and Sums of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney respectively, into the Receipt of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:190687:10"/> to the use of His Highness the Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector and the Commonwealth, and such Wife, Childe and Children shall have, hold, possess and enjoy the benefit of such Gift, Conveyance, or other settlement, Freed and Discharged as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, from such time only as such Wife, Childe and Children respectively, shall come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the said Barons, and take and subscribe the said Oath as aforesaid, and not before.</p>
            <p>And be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That no such Guardian and Guardians shall, for the making of any such Accompt as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, be bound to attend any such Auditor at his Office or Dwelling House, But such Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor, is hereby required to take such Accompt in his Circuit, in the County where such Estate doth lie, and not to receive any greater or other Fees for the same, then shall be appointed by the Commissioners of the Treasury for the time being, or any two or more of them, or by the Treasurer, Chancellour, or under Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surer of the Exchequer for the time being, or any two or more of them.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That if any Person being no Popish Recusant Convict nor Sequestred for Popish Recusancy, shall marry or take to wife, any woman that he shall know to be a Popish Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusant Convict, then upon Information exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited and proof thereof made in the Court of Exchequer, He shall be taken and adjudged a Popish Recusant Convict to all intents and purposes whatsoever, and shall be subjected and liable in his own particular Estate, real and personal, to such Seizures and Penalties, as any other Popish Recusant Convict, and shall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:190687:10"/> continue so subject and liable, untill he shall come before the said Barons of the Exchequer, and in open Court take and subscribe the said Oath, and no longer.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That no <hi>Certiorari</hi> shall, upon any pretence or Suggestion whatsoever, be granted by the Court of Vpper Bench, or by any other Court to remove any such Presentment, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction for Popish Recusancy as aforesaid, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall any such Presentment or Conviction, or any thing touching the same, be reversed for any error, or any other matter or thing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, but every such Presentment and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction shall be and remain in good force, untill such Person be Convicted, or his or her Heirs shall submit and take and subscribe the said Oath as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>Provided alwaies and be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That if any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or Persons, shall knowingly hold, possess or own, any Estate, Real or Personal, in trust for or to the use of any Recusant now under Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questration, or which shall hereafter be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, by Vertue of this Act, or shall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly suffer, his, her, or their name or names to be used in any Deed or Conveyance, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing any such Estate, which of right ought to be Seized or Sequestred to the use of His Highness the Lord Protector, and shall not within three Moneths after notice given to him or Process left at his usual place of abode, from the Lord Treasurer, or Lords Commissioners of His Highness Treasury, or Barons of the Exchequer, that he is charged or Questioned for the concealing such trust or trusts, make
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:190687:11"/> discovery thereof, That then every such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or persons, shall forfeit for such his Conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to the value of the third part of such Estate so concealed, the one Moitie to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness the Lord Protector, and the other Moitie to the Informer, to be recovered in his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness Court of Exchequer, by Bill or Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein no Essoign, Protection or Wager of Law shall be allowed.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That if the Iustices of Peace for any County, Division, Limit or Liberty, or two or more of them, shall not, according to the true intent and meaning of this Act, issue their Warrants, to all Church-wardens and Constables, requiring them to make their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentments, as aforesaid, or shall not according to the true intent and meaning of this Act, issue their Warrants unto the Constables, to Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon such persons so presented, to make their appearance and take the said Oath aforesaid, or shall not deliver such Presentment at the next Quarter Sessions, as aforesaid, then every such Iustice of Peace shall forfeit the sum of Twenty pounds; And if any such Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warden or Constable shall refuse or neglect to make such Presentment as aforesaid, Then such Constables, for every such offence, shall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit the sum of Ten pounds; And if the Clerk of the Assize, or Clerk of the Peace, shall not duely record every such Presentment, Warrant of Summons, and the execution thereof, and that without paying any Fees, they shall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit for every such offence the Sum of Twenty pounds, and that one Moitie of all Sums of money, so as above, to be forfeited by any Iustice
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:190687:11"/> of Peace, Church-warden, Constable, Clerk of the Assize, or Clerk of the Peace respectively, shall be to the use of the poor of such County, Division, Limit or Liberty respectively, where any such sum of money shall be forfeited, and the other Moity to such person or persons as shall sue for the same, in His Highness Court of Exchequer, by Bill or Information, wherein no Essoign, Protection, or Wager of Law shall be allowed.</p>
            <p>Provided also, and be it Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid, That where any Estate, that is or shall be Sequestred for the Recusancy of any Person, shall descend or come to any known Protestant, in such case He or She, to whom such Estate shall descend or come, shall repair to the Quarter Sessions of the Peace for that County, where He or She liveth, and there make it appear to the Court, That He or She is a Protestant, upon Certificate thereof, under the Hands and Seals of the Major part of the Iustices there present, to the Barons of the Exchequer (the Claim and Title to such Estate being made to appear to the said Barons) Such Person or Persons shall have his Estate dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged without paying Fees, Any thing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, or any other Law contained to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That no Person or Persons that now is sequestred or Convicted for Recusancy, or that at any time hereafter shall be Convicted for Recusancy, shall be admitted to take the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid Oath of Abjuration, unless such Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or Persons so Convicted, shall make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to the Iustices of Peace, before whom
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:190687:12"/> such Oath of Abjuration is to be taken, by the Testimony of two sufficient witnesses, at the least, upon Oath, which said Oath, the said Iustices have hereby power to Administer, That he or they have for six moneths before that time, ordinarily and frequently upon the Lords daies, repaired to some Church or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, or to some Congregational and other Christian meeting, allowed by the publique Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of these Nations, And there hath heard the Word of God preached and taught.</p>
            <p>Provided nevertheless, And it is hereby Enacted, That if any Person or Persons that is or shall be convicted for Recusancy, after such Oath taken, as is hereby directed, shall afterwards fall into Relapse, or become a Popish Recusant again, or be suspected to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Popish Recusant again, and be thereof Presented and Convicted as aforesaid, That then every such Person or Persons, shall lose all such Benefit, as He or She might otherwise, by virtue of this Act, have or enjoy by reason of His or Her taking the said Oath according to this present Act; And shall thereupon stand in such Plight, Condition and Degree, to all intents and purposes whatsoever, as though such Oath had never been taken, untill He or She (upon due Summons and Proceedings in that behalf to be had) shall again take the said Oath in such manner as before by this present Act is Limited and Appointed.</p>
            <p>And it is hereby further Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid, That it shall not be Lawfull for any Subject of this Commonwealth, (other then the House-hold-Servants that shall come over with any Ambassadour or Agent) at any
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:190687:12"/> time to be present at Mass, at the House of any such Embassadour or Agent, or any other place whatsoever, upon pain and penalty of One hundred pounds and Imprisonment, by the space of six Moneths; The one Moitie of the said forfeiture to be to the use of His Highness the Lord Protector and His Successors, and the other Moitie to the Informer; to be reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by Action Bill, Plaint, Suit or Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in any Court of Record, in which no Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soign, Protection, or Wager of Law shall be allowed.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills</hi> and <hi>John Field,</hi> Printers to His Highness the Lord Protector.</p>
            <p>1657.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>